we know humans learn from their past
experiences and machines follow
instructions given by humans but what if
humans can Turing the machines to learn
from the past data and to what humans
can do act much faster
well that's called machine learning but
it's a lot more than just learning it's
also about understanding and reasoning
so today we will learn about the basics
of machine learning so that's Paul
he loves listening to new songs he
either likes them or dislikes that Paul
decides this on the basis of the songs
tempo johner intensity and the gender of
voice for simplicity let's just use
tempo and intensity for now
so here tempo is on the x-axis ranging
from relaxed to fast whereas intensity
is on the y-axis ranging from light to
soling we see that Paul likes the song
with fast tempo and soaring intensity
while he dislikes a song with relaxed
tempo and light intensity so now we know
Paul's choices let's see Paul listens to
a new song let's name it a song a song a
has fast tempo and a soaring intensity
so it lies somewhere here looking at the
data can you guess where the ball will
like the song or not correct so Paul
likes the song by looking at Paul's past
choices we were able to classify the
unknown song very easily right let's say
now Paul listens to a new song let's
label it as song Pete so song B lies
somewhere here with medium tempo and
medium intensity neither relaxed nor
fast
neither light nor soaring now can you
guess where the Paul likes it or not not
able to guess with this Paul will like
it or dislike it other choice is unclear
correct
we could easily classify song a but when
the choice became complicated as in the
case of song P yes and that's where
machine learning comes in let's see how
in the same example for song P if we
draw a circle around the song B we see
that there are four words for like
whereas one would for dislike if we go
for the majority words we can say that
Paul will definitely like the song
that's all this was a basic machine
learning algorithm also it's called K
nearest neighbors so this is just a
small example in one of the many machine
learning algorithms quite easy right
believe me it is but what happens when
the choices become complicated as in the
case of song P that's when machine
learning comes in it learns the data
builds the prediction model and when the
new data point comes in it can easily
project for it more the data better the
model higher will be the accuracy there
are many ways in which the machine
learns it could be either supervised
learning unsupervised learning or
reinforcement learning let's first
quickly understand supervised learning
suppose your friend gives you 1 million
coins of three different currencies say
one to be one euro and one there huh
each coin has different weights for
example a coin of one rupee weighs three
grams one euro
weighs seven grams and one their own
weighs four grams your model will
predict the currency of the coin here
your weight becomes the feature of coins
while currency becomes the label when
you feed this data to the machine
learning model it learns which feature
is associated with which slip for
example it will learn that if a coin is
of three grams it will be a one rupee
coin let's give an you going to the
machine on the basis of the weight of
the new coin your model will predict the
currency hence supervised learning uses
labels data to train the model here the
Machine knew the features of the object
and also the labels associated with
those features on this note let's move
to unsupervised learning and see the
difference suppose you have cricket data
set of various players with their
respective scores and thickets taken
when you feed this data set to the
machine the machine identifies the
pattern of player performance so it
plops this data with the respective
Achatz on the x axis while runs on the y
axis while looking at the data you will
clearly see that there are two clusters
the one cluster are the players who
scored high runs and took less wickets
while the other cluster is of the
players who scored less runs but took
many wickets
so here we interpret these two clusters
as batsman and bowlers the important
point to note here is that there were no
labels of batsmen
Boulos hence the learning with unlabeled
data is unsupervised learning so we saw
a supervised learning where the data was
labeled and the unsupervised learning
where the data was unlabeled and then
there's reinforcement learning which is
a reward based learning or we can say
that it works on the principle of
feedback here let's say you provide the
system with an image of a dog and ask it
to identify it the system identifies it
as a cat so you give a negative feedback
to the Machine saying that it's a dog's
image the machine will learn from the
feedback and finally if it comes across
any other image of a dog it will be able
to classify it correctly that is
reinforcement learning to generalize
machine learning model let's see a
flowchart input is given to a machine
learning model which then gives the
output according to the algorithm
applied if it's right we take the output
as a final result else we provide
feedback to the train model and ask it
to predict until it learns
I hope you've understood supervised and
unsupervised learning so let's have a
quick quiz you have to determine whether
the given scenarios use the supervised
or unsupervised learning simple right so
now you want Facebook recognizes your
friend in a picture from an album of
tagged photographs scenario 2
Netflix recommends new movies based on
someone's past movie choices this in
Aisle 3 analyzing Bank data for
suspicious transactions and flagging
fraud transactions think wisely and
comment below your answers moving on
don't you sometimes wonder how is
machine learning possible in today's era
well that's because today we have
humongous data available everybody is
online either making a transaction or
just surfing the internet and that's
generating a huge amount of data every
minute and that data my friend is the
key to analysis also the memory handling
capabilities of computers have largely
increased which helps them to process
such a huge amount of data at hand
without any delay and yes
computers now have great computational
powers so there are a lot of
applications of machine learning out
there
to name a few machine learning is used
in healthcare where Diagnostics are
predicted for doctors review the
sentiment analysis that the tech giants
are doing on social media is another
interesting application
machine learning fraud detection in the
finance sector and also to predict
customer churn in the e-commerce sector
while booking the gap you must have
encountered surge pricing often where it
says the Farrow field trip has been
updated continue cooking yes please I'm
getting late for office well that's an
interesting machine learning model which
is used by global taxi giant uber and
others where they have differential
pricing in real time based on demand the
number of cars available bad weather
rush hour etc so they use the surge
pricing model to ensure that those who
need a cab can get one also it uses
predictive modeling to predict where the
demand will be high with the goal that
drivers can take care of the demand and
surge pricing can be minimized great hey
Siri can you remind me to book a cab at
6 p.m. today ok
I'll remind you Thanks comment below
some interesting everyday examples
around you where machines are learning
and doing amazing jobs so that's all for
machine learning basics today from my
site keep watching the space for more
interesting videos until then happy
learning